Finding Aid for Great Lakes Colleges Association Records, 1961-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Great Lakes Colleges Association Records 1961-1982
Great Lakes Colleges Association.
88339 Bi 2
Ann Arbor-based consortium of liberal arts colleges from Ohio, Indiana and Michigan formed to share resources, develop collaborative educational programs, and address common issues. Collection includes administrative records, correspondence, program proposals and reports, grant information, and content related to lobbying.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
39.5 linear feet
Records donated by the Great Lakes Colleges Association (Donor no. 6827 ) in August, 1982.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Ann Arbor-based Great Lakes Colleges Association (GLCA) was first proposed in 1959 and eventually formed in 1961 by twelve liberal arts colleges from Ohio (Antioch, Denison, Kenyon, Oberlin, Ohio Wesleyan, and Wooster), Indiana (DePauw, Earlham, and Wabash), and Michigan (Albion, Hope, and Kalamazoo). While the schools share long-standing traditions and a foundation in the Protestant revival of the early nineteenth century (and the contemporaneous westward expansion of the nation), each is distinguished by unique characteristics and various programmatic foci. Thus, Kalamazoo has a majority of its students study abroad; Kenyon is renowned for its English Department; Oberlin has a strong network in China; Earlham is closely associated with a Quaker ethos; and so on and so forth. Given the high academic standards and levels of achievement common to all the GLCA schools, these differences helped provide a basis for inter-institutional cooperation and collaboration.
Over the years, the GLCA has focused on a variety of administrative and academic initiatives that were beyond the scope of its individual member schools. Initial programs focused on international education and ways that the consortium could help share resources and enhance opportunities for students. A Ford Foundation grant in 1964 helped establish GLCA's international presence and led to programs in Japan, Lebanon, Latin America, and Yugoslavia. Opportunities in Africa, Israel, India, China, and elsewhere in Europe followed. With the success of its international program, GLCA sought to provide students the chance to immerse themselves in the urban culture of the United States and so the Philadelphia Urban Semester and the New York Arts Program were approved in 1967. Thematic off-campus programs became a hallmark of the GLCA and included studies at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory, marine biology at UC Santa-Barbara, a wilderness education program, and a partnership with the Newberry Library in Chicago. At the same time, the GLCA worked diligently to aid schools in faculty development and the overall improvement of instruction. Thus, there were various departmental (humanities, science, modern languages, etc.) and administrative (deans, admissions, financial aid, etc.) committees to share ideas and resources and various conferences, workshops, and studies to promote faculty development. The GLCA has also supported its member schools by undertaking various studies and surveys (covering everything from faculty salaries to the benefits of a liberal arts education), seeking grants and funding from a non-profit and governmental sources, and representing concerns in Washington D.C. via public testimony and lobbying.
The GLCA is governed by a Board of Directors and the association president oversees administrative issues and the execution of organizational initiatives. The office of vice-president was created in 1968 to assist the president in his responsibilities. The GLCA Board was initially composed of university presidents but GLCA bylaws were amended in 1971 to include a chief academic officer and faculty representation. Governance also takes place at additional levels, with the Faculty (later renamed Academic) Council (designed to provide faculty input on decision-making), the Dean's Council (an important source of consultation and implementation), and various committees and advisory groups involved in the operation of important GLCA programs.
The Great Lakes Colleges Association records detail the organization and administration of a progressive and innovative university consortium. The materials document the development of a range of educational programs as well as instructional initiatives. The collection will be of particular interest to those studying the opportunities posed by university consortia and the evolution of higher education in the 1960s and 70s. The GLCA records are divided into five series: Organization and Administration, Academic Programs, Other Organizations, Foundations, and Legislation and Lobbying.
Subjects:
Education--Middle West.; Universities and colleges--Middle West.
- Organization and Administration
  The Organization and Administration series contains the meeting materials of administrative entities such as the Board of Directors, university presidents, the Faculty/Academic Council, and the Deans' Council as well as the official correspondence of GLCA executives. Topical files document various GLCA committees and councils that involve personnel (deans of students, admissions officers, financial aid officers, etc.) from member schools; they also contain GLCA publications, surveys and studies, faculty development and instructional materials, and content related to the organization's history.
  - Board of Directors: meeting agendas, minutes, and related materials (including correspondence)
    - January 1962-December 1974, 31 folders (Box 1)
    - February 1975-April 1980, 17 folders (Box 2)
  - Presidents' meetings: agendas, minutes, and related materials 1966-1980, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Faculty Council: meeting materials, correspondence, and assorted proposals 1966-1970, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - Academic Council (formerly known as the Faculty Council)
    - Meeting materials, correspondence, and assorted proposals June 1970-October 1979, 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee of the Academic Council 1968-1976 (Box 3)
  - Deans' Council
    - Meeting agendas, minutes, and related materials (including correspondence)
      - May 1965-October 1977, 19 folders (Box 3)
      - March 1978-June 1980, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - General Correspondence 1976-1978 (Box 4)
  - Executive correspondence files
    - Johnson (Eldon) administration
      - General Correspondence 1962-1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Correspondence with GLCA schools and school presidents
        - Albion College to Earlham College 1962-1966, 9 folders (Box 4)
        - Hope College to College of Wooster 1962-1966, 14 folders (Box 5)
    - Acres (Henry) administration
      - Correspondence with GLCA schools and administrators 1968-1973, 12 folders (Box 6)
        (arranged alphabetically by institution)
      - Glassick (Charles): vice-presidential correspondence 1968-1969 (Box 6)
    - Fuller (Jon W.) administration
      - Washington reception 1974 (Box 6)
      - Maintaining academic integrity 1977 (Box 6)
      - General correspondence
        - December 1980-July 1981, 3 folders (Box 6)
        - August 1981-October 1981, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Neal (Don) vice-presidential correspondence 1976-1979 (Box 7)
    - Multiple administrations (Johnson, Acres, Barrett, Fuller and various vice presidents): correspondence with GLCA schools and associated administrators and faculty
      - Albion College 1962-1978, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Antioch College 1962-1978, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Denison University 1966-1978, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Depauw University 1962-1978, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Earlham College 1963-1978, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Earlham College 1973-1978 (Box 8)
      - Hope College 1965-1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Kalamazoo College 1966-1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Kenyon College 1963-1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Oberlin College 1962-1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Ohio Wesleyan University 1963-1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Wabash College 1966-1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - College of Wooster 1966-1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous 1965-1969 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous 1969-1975 (Box 9)
  - Topical files
    - Administrative Salary Survey (GLCA-ACM) 1962-1979, 6 folders (Box 9)
    - Admissions Directors
      - Meeting materials, correspondence, and reports 1962-1980, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - Monthly admissions summaries 1973-1980 (Box 9)
      - Philadelphia College fair 1979-1980 (Box 9)
    - Affirmative Action 1973 (Box 9)
    - Air Charter 1964-1967 (Box 9)
    - Athletic Directors' Meeting Materials 1968-1980, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Audiovisual Equipment Survey 1974 (Box 9)
    - Black Students (recruitment and enrollment) 1968 (Box 9)
    - Budget Review Committee 1971-1979, 7 folders (Box 10)
    - Business Officers' Meeting materials 1965-1980, 7 folders (Box 10)
    - Career Planning and Placement Officers materials 1977-1980 (Box 10)
    - Communications Council 1967-1969 (Box 10)
    - Data Sharing 1975-1979 (Box 10)
    - Deans' Newsletter 1971-1973 (Box 10)
    - Deans of Students: meetings and correspondence 1976-1979 (Box 10)
    - Development Officers 1975-1979 (Box 10)
    - Fact Book 1971 (Box 10)
    - Faculty Development: meeting materials, correspondence, and reports 1963-1978, 11 folders (Box 11)
      (includes Professional Activities Committee materials)
    - Faculty Exchange 1971-1973 (Box 11)
    - Faculty Newsletter 1967-1982 (Box 11)
    - Faculty Salary Survey 1973-1979, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Financial Aid Officers 1978-1980 (Box 11)
    - Grading Systems1971-1980, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Great Lakes Anthology literary magazine: planning materials and correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 12)
    - Higher Education Bill of Rights 1968-1969 (Box 12)
    - History
      - Audiotapes: interviews with current and former administrators about the history and formation of GLCA circa 1980, 15 audiocassettes (Box 12)
      - "The Great Lakes Colleges Association: Twenty-One Years of Cooperation in Higher Education" (Box 12)
        (organizational history written by Dr. Judith Elkin)
      - Published history working files
        - Interviews circa 1981 (Box 12)
        - Notes circa 1981, 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Related correspondence 1981-1982 (Box 12)
      - Institutional profiles, undated 1972 (Box 12)
      - Nature of consortia 1965-1976 (Box 12)
      - Origins 1960-1980 (Box 12)
      - Program brochures and reports 1962-1982 (Box 12)
    - Institutional Research 1969-1972 (Box 12)
    - Insurance 1970-1971 (Box 12)
    - Off-Campus Programs: brochures, fee information, correspondence and reports 1970-1979, 7 folders (Box 13)
    - Peace Corps program development 1965-1969 (Box 13)
    - Photographs, 1969 (Box 13)
      (Depauw University Art Center)
    - Presidents' Book on Liberal Arts Education 1976-1980, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Public Relations Audit of GLCA 1962-1978, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - Rauh-Ford Study: correspondence and reports 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Sensitivity Training 1968 (Box 14)
    - Teaching Associates 1967-1971, 2 folders (Box 14)
      (includes some photographs)
    - Trustees 1973-1975 (Box 14)
    - Tuition Remission plans, policies, and correspondence 1971-1980, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Tuition Survey 1977-1978 (Box 14)
- Academic Programs
  The Academic Programs series details the planning, operation, and evaluation of a wide range of collaborative endeavors supported by GLCA. In addition to general international education materials, there are extensive files related to specific programs abroad (Beirut, Latin America, Japan, etc.) and at home (Philadelphia Urban Semester, New York Arts Program, the Newberry Library Program, etc.). The series also illustrates GLCA members' joint development and instructional support for new established programs in areas such as Black Studies, Film, the humanities, science, art, computing, and the classics.
  - Aberdeen Program (University of Aberdeen) 1971-1978 (Box 14)
  - Africa: correspondence, programs, and meetings 1964-1973, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Art Departments
    - United States Information Agency shows 1970-1974 (Box 14)
    - Invitational exhibitions 1977-1978 (Box 14)
  - Beirut Program (American University of Beirut): program proposals, planning documents, and correspondence 1963-1976, 7 folders (Box 15)
  - Black Studies: planning materials, questionnaires, and correspondence 1968-1973 (Box 15)
  - Buddhism 1967-1968 (Box 15)
  - Classics programs: meeting materials, surveys, and correspondence 1971-1973 (Box 15)
  - Computing and computer-assisted planning: proposals, seminar materials, and correspondence 1969 (Box 15)
  - East Asian Studies: grant proposals, meeting materials, and correspondence 1964-1979, 10 folders (Box 16)
    (unarranged: May contain materials related to GLCA Japan program)
  - East Asian Studies (cont.): grant proposals, meeting materials, and correspondence 1964-1979, 10 folders (Box 17)
  - Environmental Studies: reports, correspondence, and teach-in materials 1969-1970 (Box 18)
  - Film Studies: proposals, conference materials, correspondence, etc. 1967-1976 (Box 18)
  - Fresh Water Research: conference materials, correspondence, and reports, 1970-76 (Box 18)
  - Graduate Education: meeting materials, correspondence, and surveys 1962-1964 (Box 18)
  - Higher Education Compact: proposals, meeting materials, and correspondence 1970-1973, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Humanities Program: grant proposals, meeting materials, correspondence and financial statements 1965-1969, 4 folders (Box 18)
  - Humanities Program (cont.): grant proposals, meeting materials, correspondence and financial statements 1969-1973, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - India Program: planning materials, financial statements, correspondence, etc. 1965-1977, 4 folders (Box 19)
  - International Education: grant proposals, reports, correspondence, etc. 1962-1968, 6 folders (Box 19)
    (unarranged: contains materials from various committees, task forces, and administrators)
  - International Education (cont.): grant proposals, reports, correspondence, etc. 1966-1973, 9 folders (Box 20)
  - International Education (cont.): grant proposals, reports, correspondence, etc. 1971-1977, 8 folders (Box 21)
  - Israel Program 1971-1974 (Box 21)
  - Japan Program: meeting materials, finances, and correspondence 1963-1973, 5 folders (Box 21)
  - Japan Program: meeting materials, finances, and correspondence 1974-1978, 5 folders (Box 22)
  - Language and Area Studies: meeting materials, reports, and correspondence 1964-1968, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Latin American Program: meeting materials, finances, correspondence related to programs in Mexico, Colombia, etc. 1962-1968, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Latin American Program (cont.): meeting materials, finances, correspondence related to programs in Mexico, Colombia, etc. 1968-1977, 4 folders (Box 23)
  - Librarians 1964-1978 (Box 23)
  - Marine Biology: grant proposals, meeting materials, and correspondence 1961-1977, 7 folders (Box 23)
    (includes some materials related to the Argonne National Laboratory)
  - Marshall Scholars 1976-1980 (Box 24)
  - Medical Education Report 1975 (Box 24)
  - Music Departments 1978 (Box 24)
  - NEH East Asia Institutes: proposals, evaluations, and correspondence 1975-1978 (Box 24)
  - Newberry Library Program: reports, correspondence, and meeting materials 1974-1977 (Box 24)
  - New Writer's Award: meeting materials, press releases, and correspondence 1968-1980, 5 folders (Box 24)
  - New York Arts Program: correspondence, reports, and student information 1967-1972, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - New York Arts Program (cont.): correspondence, reports, and student information 1972-1978, 4 folders (Box 25)
  - Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL): correspondence, reports, and financial materials 1969-1977, 5 folders (Box 25)
  - Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) (cont.): correspondence, reports, and financial materials 1976-1978, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Philadelphia Urban Semester Program: meeting materials, reports, and correspondence 1967-1971, 5 folders (Box 26)
  - Philadelphia Urban Semester Program (cont.): meeting materials, reports, and correspondence 1969-1978, 8 folders (Box 27)
  - Philadelphia Urban Semester Program (cont.): meeting materials, reports, and correspondence 1976-1981, 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Poland Seminar: grants materials, correspondence, and reports 1973-1975, 6 folders (Box 28)
  - Programmed Instruction Project: correspondence, reports, and financial materials 1962-1966, 5 folders (Box 28)
  - Russian Studies Center: meeting materials and correspondence 1968-1970 (Box 29)
  - Science Faculty Committee: meeting materials and correspondence 1961-1969, 2 folders (Box 29)
  - Social Science, Philosophy of: conference materials and correspondence 1971-1972 (Box 29)
  - Social Work Education 1968-1969 (Box 29)
  - Speech and Theater Departments: proposals and correspondence 1969-1972 (Box 29)
  - Teaching and Learning Committee: meeting materials, correspondence, and reports 1967-1972 (Box 29)
  - Undergraduate Science Education 1963-1964 (Box 29)
  - Underprivileged, Task Force on the: meeting materials and correspondence 1968-1969 (Box 29)
  - Urban Studies Program: reports, meeting materials, and correspondence 1968-1975, 7 folders (Box 29)
    (contains materials related to Philadelphia Urban Semester and international urban programs)
  - Wilderness Program: proposals, correspondence, and reports, 1973-75, 7 folders (Box 30)
  - Women's Studies Program: proposals, conference materials, correspondence, etc. 1976-1980, 11 folders (Box 30)
  - Yugoslavia (Urban Studies) Program: seminar materials, reports, and correspondence 1968-1970, 3 folders (Box 30)
  - Yugoslavia (Urban Studies) Program (cont.): seminar materials, reports, and correspondence 1972-1976, 3 folders (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous 1964-1979 (Box 31)
    (contains materials related to various GLCA academic programs)
- Other Organizations
  The Other Organizations series documents GLCA's interaction with a wide range of groups that include like-minded consortia (such as the Associated Colleges of the Midwest), local school districts (Ann Arbor and Detroit), higher education associations and councils, and other universities.
  - American Association for Higher Education (AAHE) 1970-1978, 4 folders (Box 31)
  - American Council on Education (ACE) 1966-1978, 3 folders (Box 31)
  - American Institute of Indian Studies 1962-1970, 2 folders (Box 31)
  - Ann Arbor Schools 1971-1972 (Box 31)
  - Argonne Universities Association 1968-1970 (Box 31)
  - Associated Colleges of the Midwest (ACM) 1962-1968 (Box 31)
  - Associated Colleges of the Midwest (ACM) (cont.) 1969-1979, 7 folders (Box 32)
  - Associated Colleges of the Midwest (ACM) GLCA Merger Discussions 1973, 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Association of American Colleges (AAC) 1963-1972, 3 folders (Box 32)
  - Association of American Colleges (AAC) (cont.) 1973-1979, 3 folders (Box 33)
  - Association of Governing Boards (AGB) 1974-1978 (Box 33)
  - Center for Research and Development in Higher Education 1967-1971 (Box 33)
  - College Center of the Finger Lakes 1962-1971, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Council for Advancement and Support of Education (CASE) 1978 (Box 33)
  - Council for Intercultural Studies and Programs (CISP) 1972-1974, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Council for Interinstitutional Leadership 1976-1978 (Box 33)
  - Council on International Educational Exchange (CIEE) 1963-1970 (Box 33)
  - Council on International Educational Exchange (CIEE) (cont.) 1970-1979, 3 folders (Box 34)
  - Detroit Public Schools 1965-1966 (Box 34)
  - Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies 1975-1976 (Box 34)
  - Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research-ICPSR (U of M) 1975-1978 (Box 34)
  - Kansas City Regional Council for Higher Education 1971-1978 (Box 34)
  - National Advisory Council on Women's Educational Programs (NACWEP) 1977-1980, 5 folders (Box 34)
  - National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities-NAICU 1976-1979, 2 folders (Box 35)
  - National Center for Higher Education 1970-1976 (Box 35)
  - National Council of Associations for International Studies (NCAIS) 1969-1972, 3 folders (Box 35)
  - Netherlands Information Service 1967-1973 (Box 35)
  - Pomona College 1974-1979 (Box 35)
  - University of Michigan 1969-1978, 3 folders (Box 35)
  - University of Toledo (Center for the Study of Higher Education) 1969-1971 (Box 35)
  - Washington University 1975-1978 (Box 36)
  - White Freedom School 1968-1971 (Box 36)
  - Wittenberg University 1976-1977 (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous: other institutions 1962-1979, 5 folders (Box 36)
- Foundations
  The Foundations series includes grant proposals, reports, and correspondence directed to various foundations and government entities. Of particular interest are the materials related to the Ford Foundation, which provided an essential grant early in the GLCA's history.
  - Arthur Vining Davis Foundation 1967-1969 (Box 36)
  - Asia Foundation 1962-1975 (Box 36)
  - Carnegie Corporation 1962-1973 (Box 36)
  - Danforth Foundation 1963-1979, 3 folders (Box 36)
  - Dupont Corporation 1967-1968 (Box 36)
  - Ford Foundation 1961-1973, 5 folders (Box 36)
  - Ford Foundation 1961-1973, 6 folders (Box 37)
  - Johnson Foundation 1962-1972 (Box 37)
  - IBM Math Seminar 1970-1971 (Box 37)
  - Kettering Foundation 1964-1969, 3 folders (Box 37)
  - Lilly Endowment 1971-1978, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - National Endowment for the Arts 1967-1978 (Box 37)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities 1967-1980, 7 folders (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous grant requests 1968-1969 (Box 37)
- Legislation and Lobbying
  The Legislation and Lobbying series covers the GLCA's involvement with highly relevant legislation and also documents the consortium's lobbying efforts. The series includes materials related to various pieces of legislation as well as public testimony from GLCA representatives.
  - Action 1972 (Box 38)
  - Ahead (Dept. of Defense) 1975 (Box 38)
  - Energy Research and Development Administration (ERDA) 1976 (Box 38)
  - 1977 (Box 38)
  - Federal Student Financial Aid 1973-1976 (Box 38)
  - Fund for the Improvement of Post-Secondary Education (FIPSE) 1976-1979 (Box 38)
  - Handicapped Education 1977 (Box 38)
  - Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW) 1971-1977, 2 folders (Box 38)
  - Higher Education Financing (joint ACM-GLCA initiative) 1969-1973 (Box 38)
  - Independent Colleges Office (ICO) 1976-1980, 4 folders (Box 38)
  - Midwestern College Office (MCO) 1971-1973 (Box 38)
  - Midwestern College Office (MCO) (cont.) 1972-1976, 6 folders (Box 39)
  - National Defense Education Act (NDEA) 1975-1976, 3 folders (Box 39)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF) 1966-1979, 4 folders (Box 39)
  - State Department 1962-1970 (Box 39)
  - Testimony Related to Legislation 1969-1979, 5 folders (Box 40)
  - Washington Representation 1975-1976 (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous 1966-1978 (Box 40)